A Guide to the National Agricultural Publications, 1917-present
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
National Agricultural Publications, 1917-present
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2011-022
0.8 cu. ft. 2 boxes
The collection contains United States Department of Agriculture, War Food Administration, and other national agency publications from the early 20th century to the present day.
United States. Agricultural Research Service.; United States. Dept. of Agriculture.; United States. Dept. of Health and Human Services.; United States. Division of Home Economics.; United States. War Food Administration.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The original donation was acquired by Special Collections prior to 2009. Additional publications were donated to Special Collections in 2010 and were integrated with existing materials. Future accruals are expected.
Scope and Content
The collection contains United States Department of Agriculture, War Food Administration, and other national agency publications on topics ranging from war-time food use and Victory gardens, kitchen appliances, preservation strategies, individual foods/food groups, and home demonstration. Publications date from 1917 to the present day.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into four series, based on broad categories of publications. Series I: Food, Cooking and Nutrition includes publications about nutrition and health, specific foods, recipes, and food preservation. Series II: Home Economics and Household Management contains publications about home appliances, simple home repair, sewing, and laundry. Series III: Furnishings and Home Organization has publications about kitchen, bathroom, and laundry organization, purchase and maintenance of furnishings, and building home storage. Series IV: Farm and Garden includes publications relating to creation and maintenance of farm buildings, crop blights and diseases, soil conservation, and care of animals. Please note: There is some overlap between series.
Within each series, publications are arranged in chronological order with undated materials at the end.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Ms2001-004, Ann A. Hertzler Collection. Finding aid available online.
Ms2011-021, Janet L. Cameron Collection. Finding aid available online.
Ms2012-040, Virginia Tech Special Collections State/Regional Agricultural Publications. Finding aid available online.
RG 26/2, Agricultural Extension Service (now Virginia Cooperative Extension Service) Records. A brief description of the materials in this University Archives record group is available online: http://spec.lib.vt.edu/archives/guide/rg26.htm.
Special Collections houses more than 300 publications by the Virginia Cooperative Extension Service. Publications may be found by searching the library's catalog, Addison, for author: Virginia Cooperative Extension Service.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Agricultural extension work; History of Food and Drink; Home demonstration work; Home economics; Nutrition
Contents List
- Series I: Food, Cooking, and Nutrition
  - 1917-1939 (Box-folder 1-1)
    Bibliography
    Round, L. A., and H. L. Lang. Preservation of Vegetables by Fermentation and Salting. Farmers' Bulletin 881. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1917.
    Close, C. P. Homemade Fruit Butters. Farmers' Bulletin 900. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1917.
    LeFevre, Edwin. Making Fermented Pickles. Farmers' Bulletin 1438. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1927.
    Matheson, Kenneth J. and Jessie M. Hoover. Making and Using Cottage Cheese in the Home. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1451. Washington, D.C.: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1927.
    White, William. Making Butter on the Farm. Farmers' Bulletin 876. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1924.
    Stanley, Louis. Canning Fruits and Vegetables at Home. Farmers' Bulletin 1471. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1931.
    Alexander, Lucy M., and Fanny Walker Yeatman. Cooking Cured Pork. Leaflet 81. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1931.
    Whiteman, Elizabeth Fuller, and Fanny Walker Yeatman. Honey and Some of Its Uses. Leaflet 113. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1936.
    King, Florance B., and Adelle B. Freeman. Homemade Bread, Cake, and Pastry. Farmers' Bulletin 1775. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1938.
  - 1940-1943 (Box-folder 1-2)
    Haskell, R. J., and V. R. Boswell. Disease-Resistant Varieties of Vegetables for the Home Garden. Leaflet 203. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1940.
    Stanley, Louise, Mabel Stienbarger, and Dorothy Shank. Home Canning of Fruits, Vegetables, and Meats. Farmers' Bulletin 1762. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1941.
    United States. Dried Fruits in Low Cost Meals. Washington: U.S. Govt. print. off, 1942.
    United States. "Victory Food Special: Fresh Apples." Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1942.
    United States. How to Make Your Ironing Equipment Last Longer. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1942
    United States. Apple Recipes. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1942
    United States. Fight Food Waste in the Home. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1942. (2 copies)
    Alexander, Lucy M., and Fanny Walker Yeatman. Meat for Thrifty Meals. Farmers' Bulletin 1908. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1942.
    Beattie, James H., and Dean H. Rose. Home Storage of Vegetables and Fruits. Farmers' Bulletin 1939. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1943.
    United States. Why Feed the Insects?: Protect the Dried Foods in Your Home. Washington, D.C.: U.S. G.P.O., 1943.
    United States. School Lunch Recipes. Miscellaneous Publication 537. Washington, D.C.: The Bureau, 1943.
    United States. Fats in Wartime Meals. Washington, D.C.: Bureau of Human Nutrition and Home Economics, Agricultural Research Administration, U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1943.
    Boswell, Victor R. Victory Gardens. Miscellaneous Publication 483. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1943.
    Hewston, Elizabeth M., and Rosemary L. Marsh. Vitamin Values of Foods in Terms of Common Measures. Miscellaneous Publication 505. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1943.
    United States. Menu-Planning Guide for School Lunches Based on FDA Requirements for Type A and Type B Lunches. Washington, D.C.: War Food Administration, Food Distribution Administration, 1943.
  - 1944-1951 (Box-folder 1-3)
    United States. Pickle and Relish Recipes. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1944.
    United States. Home Canning of Fruits and Vegetables: Points for Success. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1947.
    United States. Home Freezers: Their Selection and Use. Miscellaneous Publication 687. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1949.
    United States. Family Fare: Food Management and Recipes. Home and Garden Bulletin 1. Washington, D.C.: The Bureau, 1950.
    United States. Pots and Pans for Your Kitchen. Home and Garden Bulletin 2. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, August 1950.
    United States. Home Freezing of Fruits and Vegetables. Home and Garden Bulletin 10. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1951.
    United States. Freezing Combination Main Dishes. Home and Garden Bulletin 40. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, July 1954.
  - 1955-1976 (Box-folder 1-4)
    United States. Money-Saving Main Dishes. Home and Garden Bulletin 43. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1955.
    United States. Turkey on the Table the Year Round. Home and Garden Bulletin 45. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1958.
    United States. Pork in Your Meals. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1959.
    United States. Making Pickles and Relishes at Home. Home and Garden Bulletin 92. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1970.
    United States. Home Freezing of Fruits and Vegetables. Home and Garden Bulletin 10. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1976.
  - 1977-1985 (Box-folder 1-5)
    United States. Nutrition and Your Health: Dietary Guidelines for Americans. Home and Garden Bulletin No. 232. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture/U.S. Dept. of Health and Human Services, February 1980.
    United States. Eating for Better Health. Food and Nutrition Service Program Aid No. 1290. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, August 1981.
    United States. Sodium: Think About It.... Home and garden bulletin, no. 237. Washington: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1982.
    United States. Talking about Turkey: How to Buy, Store, Thaw, Stuff, and Prepare Your Holiday Bird. Home and Garden Bulletin Number 243, October 1984.
    Parmley, Mary Ann. The Safe Food Book: Your Kitchen Guide. Home and Garden Bulletin Number 241. Washington: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, June 1985.
    United States. Nutrition and Your Health: Dietary Guidelines for Americans. Home and Garden Bulletin No. 232, Second edition. Washington: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1985.
  - 1986-1999 (Box-folder 1-6)
    United States. Nutrition and Your Health: Dietary Guidelines for Americans: Eat a Variety of Foods. Home and Garden Bulletin Number 232-1. Washington: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, April 1986.
    United States. Nutrition and Your Health: Dietary Guidelines for Americans: Maintain Desirable Weight. Home and Garden Bulletin Number 232-2. Washington: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, April 1986.
    United States. Nutrition and Your Health: Dietary Guidelines for Americans: Avoid Too Much Fat, Saturate Fat, and Cholesterol. Home and Garden Bulletin Number 232-3. Washington: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, April 1986.
    United States. Nutrition and Your Health: Dietary Guidelines for Americans: Eat Foods with Adequate Starch and Fiber. Home and Garden Bulletin Number 232-4. Washington: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, April 1986.
    United States. Nutrition and Your Health: Dietary Guidelines for Americans: Avoid Too Much Sugar. Home and Garden Bulletin Number 232-5. Washington: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, April 1986.
    United States. Nutrition and Your Health: Dietary Guidelines for Americans: Avoid Too Much Sodium. Home and Garden Bulletin Number 232-6. Washington: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, April 1986.
    United States. Nutrition and Your Health: Dietary Guidelines for Americans: If You Drink Alcoholic Beverages, Do So In Moderation. Home and Garden Bulletin Number 232-7. Washington: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, April 1986.
    Parmley, Mary Ann. Safe Food to Go--A Guide to Packing Lunches, Picknicking & Camping Out. Home and Garden Bulletin Number 242. Washington: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, May 1986.
    United States. Dietary Guidelines and Your Diet: Home Economics Teacher's Guide. Miscellaneous Publication Number 1457. Washington: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, February 1988.
    United States. Feeding Infants: A Guide for Use in the Child Care Food Program. FNS-258. Washington: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, December 1988.
    United States. A Planning Guide for Food Service in Child Care Centers. FNS-64. Washington: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, July 1989.
    United States. Nutrition and Your Health: Dietary Guidelines for Americans. Third edition. Washington: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1990.
    Action Guide for Healthy Eating. [Bethesda, Md.?]: National Institutes of Health, National Cancer Institute, [1995] Available online.
  - 2000-present (Box-folder 1-8)
    Down Home Healthy Cookin'. [Bethesda, Md.?]: National Institutes of Health, National Cancer Institute, [2000]. Available online.
  - Undated (Box-folder 1-7)
    United States. A Word About Low-Sodium Diets. HHS Publication No. (FDA) 84-2179. Washington: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services.
    United States. 'Can-venient' Ways with Shrimp. Bureau of Commercial Fisheries.
- Series II: Home Economics and Household Management
  - 1920-1929 (Box-folder 2-1)
    United States. Homemade Fireless Cookers and Their Use. Farmers' Bulletin No. 771. Washington: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1921.
    Lang, Harold L., and Anna Horton Whittelsey Hoyt. Stain Removal from Fabrics: Home Methods. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1474. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1926.
  - 1930-1939 (Box-folder 2-2)
    Warren, George M. Simple Plumbing Repairs in the Home. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1460. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1936.
    O'Brien, Ruth, and Helen S. Holbrook. Methods and Equipment for Home Laundering. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1497. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1937.
    Warren, George M. Making Cellars Dry. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1572.[Washington, D.C.]: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1938.
    United States. Consumers' Guide. Vol. V, No. 13. Washington, D.C.: Consumers' Counsel of the Agricultural Adjustment Administration, [December 5] 1938.
    Smither, F. W. Washing, Cleaning, and Polishing Materials. Circular of the National Bureau of Standards C424. Washington: U. S, Department of Commerce, August 1939.
  - 1940-1949 (Box-folder 2-3)
    Moffett, Carol Willis. House Cleaning Management and Methods. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1834. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1940.
    Morrison, Bess Viemont. Slip Covers for Furniture. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1873. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1941.
    Furry, Margaret Smith. Stain Removal from Fabrics Home Methods. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1474. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1942.
    United States. How to Make Your Ironing Equipment Last Longer. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1942.
    Scott, Clarice Louisba. ABC's of Mending. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1925. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1946.
    Warren, George M., and John Wesley Rockey. Simple Plumbing Repairs in the Home. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1460. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1948.
    United States. Preventing and Removing Mildew: Home Methods. Washington, D.C.: Bureau of Human Nutrition and Home Economics, U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1948.
    McCracken, Earl C. Home Freezers: Their Selection and Use. Miscellaneous Publication No. 687. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1949.
  - 1950-1959 (Box-folder 2-4)
    Furry, Margaret Smith. Detergents for Home Laundering. Home and Garden Bulletin No. 49. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1956.
    United States. Automatic Clothes Dryers-Their Performance and Effect on Certain Fabric Properties. Home Economics Research Report No. 6. Washington: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, October 1958.
  - 1960-1969 (Box-folder 2-13)
    United States. How to Prevent and Remove Mildew: Home Methods. Home and Garden Bulletin No. 68. Washington: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, June 1964.
    United States. Sanitation in Home Laundering. Home and Garden Bulletin No. 97. Washington: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, August 1964.
    United States. Simple Plumbing Repairs for the Home and Farmstead. Farmers' Bulletin No. 2202. Washington: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, September 1964.
    United States. Washing Machines: Selection and Use. Home and Garden Bulletin No.328. Washington: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, December 1964.
    United States. Removing Stains from Fabrics: Home Methods. Home and Garden Bulletin No. 62. Washington: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, April 1965.
    United States. Home Laundering: The Equipment and the Job. Home and Garden Bulletin No. 101. Washington: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, May 1965.
    United States. Clean Windows, Mirrors, and Other Glass--For a Clean House. Washington: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, June 1966.
    United States. A Clean Refrigerator-For a Clean House.. Washington: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, July 1966.
    United States. When to Do House Cleaning Jobs. Washington: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, July 1966.
    United States. Many Hands Make Housework Light. Washington: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, July 1966.
    United States. Clean Clothes Closets-For a Clean House. Washington: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, July 1966.
    United States. A Clean House is Important. Washington: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, July 1966.
    United States. Clean Walls, Ceilings, and Woodwork-For a Clean House. Washington: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, July 1966.
    United States. Clean Upholstered Furniture-For a Clean House. Washington: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, October 1967.
    United States. Clean Beds--For a Clean House. Washington: U. S. Dept. of Agriculture, October 1967.
- Series III: Furnishings and Home Organization
  - 1920-1929 (Box-folder 2-5)
    United States. Floors and Floor Coverings. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1219. Washington: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1921.
  - 1930-1939 (Box-folder 2-6)
    National Committee on Wood Utilization (U.S.). You Can Make It for Camp and Cottage: Practical Uses for Secondhand Wooden Containers and Odd Pieces of Lumber: Report of the Subcommittee on Camp and Cottage Equipment of the National Committee on Wood Utilization: Sixteenth Report of a Series on the Marketing and Use of Lumber. Washington, D.C.: U.S. G.P.O., 1930.
  - 1940-1949 (Box-folder 2-7)
    Edwards, Elma, J. Robert Dodge, and Maud Wilson. Closets and Storage Spaces. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1865. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1940.
    Senner, Arthur H., and T. A. H. Miller. Fireplaces and Chimneys. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1889. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1941.
    Easy-to-Build Kitchen Cabinets for the Remodeled Farmhouse. Miscellaneous Publication No. 680. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1949. Publication is also available online.
  - 1960-1969 (Box-folder 2-8)
    Tayloe, Genevieve K., W. Russell Parker, and Mildred S. Howard. Bathrooms. Miscellaneous Publication No. 988. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1965.
    Harper, Mildred S., and W. Russell Parker. Planning Bathrooms for Today's Homes. Home and Garden Bulletin No. 99. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1967.
    Howard, Mildred S., Genevieve K. Tayloe, and W. Russell Parker. L-Shaped Kitchen Arrangements. Miscellaneous Publication No. 935. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1963. Also available online.
- Series IV: Farm and Garden
  - 1930-1939 (Box-folder 2-9)
    McAtee, W. L. Usefulness of Birds on the Farm. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1682. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1931. Also available online.
    Mulford, Furman Lloyd. Rockeries. Leaflet No. 90. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1932.
    Beattie, James H. Sash Greenhouses. Leaflet No. 124. Washington D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1937.
  - 1940-1949 (Box-folder 2-10)
    Shepherd, J. B., and Fred W. Miller. Feeding, Care, and Management of Young Dairy Stock. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1723. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1940.
    United States. Electric Light for the Farmstead. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1838. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1940.
    Haskell, Royal J., and Victor R. Boswell. Disease-Resistant Varieties of Vegetables for the Home Garden. Leaflet No. 203. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1940.
    Beattie, W. R. Hotbeds and Coldframes. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1743. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1941.
    Ross, W. Arthur, Joseph Jay Deiss, Ward Powers Beard, and Lee C. Prickett. Building Electrical Equipment for the Farm. Vocational Division Bulletin No. 209. Washington, D.C.: Federal Security Agency, U.S. Office of Education, 1941.
    Bregger, John T., and Grover F. Brown. Conserving Soil and Moisture in Orchards and Vineyards. Farmers' Bulletin No. 1970. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1945.
    White, W. H., and S. P. Doolittle. A Vegetable Gardener's Handbook on Insects and Diseases. Miscellaneous Publication No. 605. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1946.
  - 1950-1959 (Box-folder 2-11)
    Dodge, J. Robert, and E. G. Molander. Preventing Storm Wind Damage to Farm Buildings. Agricultural Information Bulletin No. 144. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, 1956.
  - 1960-1969 (Box-folder 2-12)
    United States. Insects and Diseases of Vegetables in the Home Garden. Home and Garden Bulletin No. 46. Washington: U.S. Govt. Print. Off, 1961.